Guide to the Carol H. Meyer papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Carol H. Meyer Papers,
1954-1995.
Meyer, Carol H., 1924-
6.72 linear feet (16 document boxes).
Columbia University. Columbia University Archives Rare Book and Manuscript Library. New York, NY. 10027
6761350
Dr. Carol H. Meyer taught clinical and advanced social work practice in the School of Social Work (1962-1995). The papers consist primarily of her teaching files, but also include correspondence, papers, speeches, and material related to her research and projects.
Biographical Note
Carol H. Meyer, a native of Brooklyn, was born on March 18, 1924 in New York City. Meyer received a Bachelor's degree from the University of Pittsburgh in 1946 and a Master's degree in Social Work from the New York School of Social Work later the Columbia School of Social Work in 1949. She received the first Ph.D. in casework awarded by the Columbia School of Social Work in 1957.
Meyer began her career in social work as a group worker at Greenwich House in New York City. While completing her education, Meyer gained experience as a group worker, case worker, and supervisor. She also taught at the New York University School of Social Work from 1956-1959, and then served as an assistant to the New York City Welfare Commissioner as Director of Training from 1959-1962. Meyer joined Columbia University as an Associate Professor in 1962, and taught clinical and advanced social work practice. She was granted tenure in 1965, and became a full professor in 1966. She remained at the University for the rest of her career.
Meyer was an authority on child and family welfare and mental health. Her work also dealt with the eco-system perspective, or the concept that a range of factors should be considered in the creation or assessment of a social service or treatment plan. Meyer was also considered a leader in national social work education; she served on the educational board of the British Journal of Social Work and on the board of the Council on Social Work Education.
Meyer's work was widely published in professional journals on child welfare casework, psychiatric and family practice, foster care, women, and social work. She also lectured throughout the United States, Canada, and the United Kingdom. She published five books: Staff Development in Public Welfare Agencies (1966), Social Work Practice: A Response to the Crisis (1970), Clinical Social Work in the Eco-Systems Perspective (1983), Social Work with the Aging (1986), and Assessment in Social Work Practice (1993). She also served as an editor for other book projects and as the editor in chief of Affilia: Journal of Women in Social Work in the early 1990s.
Meyer died of cancer on December 2, 1996, in New York City. She was survived by two sisters and a brother.
Scope and Content
Meyer's papers consist primarily of teaching files from her work at the Columbia University School of Social Work, but also include correspondence, papers, speeches, and material related to research and outside projects.
Meyer's teaching files include material related to both her own courses and the general curriculum in the School of Social Work, particularly in areas related to the social work practice sequence of courses and doctoral examinations for practice work. Her teaching files not only include her own course materials, but often also include bibliographies, course outlines, and reading lists from other professors. Meyer also kept readings and notes on subjects related to course topics filed with her teaching files. Meyer's early teaching career is not well documented in her papers; most of her files appear related to courses taught between 1976-1995. There is also no documentation of Meyer's work in the larger university community.
Meyer's papers do not extensively document her research work. The collection includes one folder of various reprints and editorials (1959-1994). In addition, there is documentation related to two other projects; "The Homeless Seriously and Persistently Mentally Ill" (1989) and Assessment in Social Work Practice (1993).
The papers do contain material related to Meyer's work within the social work profession. Meyer was involved in outside consulting, speaking engagements, task forces, and training, and her papers include files on many of these activities. There is no coverage of her educational or professional activities prior to 1959.
The papers do not contain any material related to Meyer's personal life or interests.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series.
Series I: Curriculum and Teaching Files, 1954-1995, Undated
Series II: Professional Activities, 1960-1990
Subseries II.1: General, 1967-1988
Subseries II.2: Papers and Speeches, 1968-1990
Subseries II.3: Projects, 1960-1986
Series III: Publications and Related Files, 1959-1994
Subjects
Columbia University.--School of Social Work--Faculty.; Meyer, Carol H., 1924-; Social case work--United States.; Social case work--United States--Methodology.; Social service.; Social work education--Curricula--United States.; Social work education--United States.; Correspondence.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
The papers were received as a bequest of the Estate of Carol H. Meyer via the School of Social Work in 1998.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Curriculum and Teaching Files, 1954-1995
  This series contains files related to curriculum and courses taught in the School of Social Work. The majority of the course files relate to courses taught between approximately 1976-1995. Meyer's course files include articles, assignments, bibliographies, course outlines, examination questions, handouts, reading lists, and Meyer's own reading materials and notes on various subjects related to course topics. Some of Meyer's files also relate to development of curriculum in the School of Social Work, particularly as related to doctoral examinations and the social work practice sequence. These files include correspondence, course outlines, examination questions, meeting notes, and memoranda.
  - 6601--Assignment, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Depression, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    (6113--The Depressed Client)
  - 7113, Undated
    (The Context of Social Work Practice)
    - Family and Children in Health (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Class Notes (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Assessment Outlines, 1990, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 7113 and 7115, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 7115
    (Clinical Social Work Practice)
    - 7115, 1987-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Loss and Separation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Course Materials, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Crisis Theory, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 8201 circa 1987-1993
    (Social Work Practice)
    - Practice Theory (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Task, 1987, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Research Notes 8201, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Susan Kemp, 1990, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    (Dissertation Proposal and Drafts)
  - Child Care, 1988-1990, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    (Includes case outline for 6921--Day Care)
  - Population Policy, 1969-1986, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Child Abuse, 1977-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    (Includes course materials for 6920, 7115)
  - Exams, 1975-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    (Courses 6920, 6921 on Family and Children's Services)
  - Permanency/Prevention, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    (Child Welfare Preventative Services)
  - Separation/Deprivation, 1978-1983, Undated, (3 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Foster Care
    - 1980-1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1980-1993, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Children Against Mothers, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sexuality, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Impact of Mental Illness on Children, 1978, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Divorce, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Step Families, 1980-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    (Course Material for 6920, 7115)
  - Schizophrenia, 1988-1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    (Includes course material for 6601, 6602)
  - 6601
    - Course Outlines, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Ethnicity/Culture, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Aging, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Depression, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      (Includes course material for 7113)
    - Borderline Personality, circa 1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 7115
    - Adolescence, 1982-1989, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Children Coping with Stress (Abuse, Alcoholism), 1980s (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Orphan's Progress, 1965-1969, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Impact of Mental Illness on Children, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Ethics, circa 1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - AIDS, 1980-1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      (7115--AIDS--Death and Dying)
    - Alcoholism and Substance Abuse, 1982-1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Subject Areas
    - Untitled, 1987-1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      (Mostly readings and notes on depression)
    - Substance Abuse, circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      (Includes reading list for 7115)
    - Dual Diagnosis, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Advocacy, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      (Includes course materials for 6112, 7102)
    - Termination, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      (Includes reading lists for 7101)
  - Practice Theory
    - 7115, 1990-1995, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
    - Research and Practice Articles #8201 1970-1984, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
    - Family Treatment, 1954-1981, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - DSW Exams, 1979-1995 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 8201 Midterm, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Practice Models, 1981-1982, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Epistemology - Family Treatment (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Course 8201
    - Mrs. P: A Problem Redefined, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      (Case study, notes, and class assignment for 6113)
    - Ego Theory/Ego Psychology, 1982-1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Advanced Practice Memos, 1980-1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      (Memos on the practice sequence of courses in the advanced program; the PhD requirement, etc.)
  - 6601 and 7701, 1990-1991, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Meeting for Second Year Practice Teachers, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Course 6104, 1976-1980, Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    (Social Work Practice 4)
  - Loneliness, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    (Includes conference materials and Meyer's comments)
  - 8203 Seminar in Advance Social Work Practice
    - 8203, 1978-1984 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Manpower and Practice, 1968, 1973, Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
      (8201)
    - Inter-professional Practice and Education, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Self-Help Groups, circa 1982 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - 6601, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 7102 Social Work Practice, 1969-1985 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Child Abuse and Violence, 1978-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
  - Untitled 1981 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    (Various materials on a course on Human Behavior and the Social Environment from Hunter College)
  - 7102, 1985-1987 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 6601
    - 1981-1991, Undated, (4 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 7-9)
    - Course Binder
      - 1989-1991 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 7113 circa 1992
    - Course Pack (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Additional Articles (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Social Work Practice (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Classic General Papers (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 7101 Group Methods, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Group Work
    - 1982, Undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - 1984, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - 6920 Family and Children's Services, 1992-1995, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 8201, 1990-1995 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified Notebook, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    (Includes material on a Practice Teacher's meeting and the practice sequence of courses)
  - Untitled, 1980-1985 (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
    (Includes material for 6601 and 7102, mainly on families and gender roles)
  - 7115 Clinical Social Work Practice, circa 1990 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Adoption, 1970s, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Schools (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Groups, 1986-1991 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    (Includes memos to practice teachers and course materials for 7101)
  - School Material
    - Practice Sequence, 1988-1990 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      (Includes course material for 7115)
    - Doctoral Examination in Advanced Practice, 1983-1992 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Fields of Practice, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Howard Case, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    (Case material for 6204)
  - Social Work Practice Sequence
    - Practice Outlines--MSW/DSW, 1970, 1986-1989 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Clinical Practice DSW/MSW--Curriculum Proposals, 1983-1987 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Social Work Practice III, Undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
      (Course 7113)
    - Fields of Practice, Undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
      (Social Work Practice V, Course 7115)
    - Human Behavior and Social Environment (HBSE), Undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Social Work Practice II, 1991, Undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
      (Course 7102)
    - Practice, Programming and Supervision (PPS), 1991, Undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
      (7133 7135)
    - Social Work Practice Sequence, circa 1991 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      (Course 7115)
    - Foundations (Social Work Practice I and Practice, Programming and Supervision I), 1990-1992, Undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Field Work Curriculum, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Issues of Diversity, Educational Methods, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      (Course 7710)
    - School--Practice CHM--Special Memos/Reports, 1971-1987, (2 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - 6920
    - Placement, 1992-1995, Undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - 6920 Family and Children Services, 1995, (2 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Untitled (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Domestic Violence (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
      (articles, notes)
    - Classification Problem/Treatment (Box 16, Folder 5)
      (includes reading list for course 6201)
    - 6920 Course Pack, 1995 Fall (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Series II: Professional Activities, 1960-1990
  Series II contains a curriculum vita (1987), correspondence, and files related to Meyer's papers, presentations, speeches, and work on projects outside of Columbia University.
  - Subseries II.1: General, 1967-1988
    consists of Meyer's personal file and general professional correspondence.
    - Personal, 1967-1987 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      (Includes correspondence, curriculum vita (1987), and other material)
    - Professional Correspondence, circa 1968-1988 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II.2: Papers and Speeches, 1968-1990
    includes copies of Meyer's speeches and presentation papers.
    - Speeches, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - CHM Speeches--CUSSW
      - 1977-1988 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - 1977-1988, (2 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - CHM Speeches, 1972-1989 (Box 13, Folder 3-5)
    - Papers (CHM)
      - 1981-1989, (2 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 6-8)
      - 1981-1989 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - New Jersey School of Social Work, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Papers and Speeches, 1972, 1987-1990 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Subseries II.3: Projects, 1960-1986
    consists of a set of files on task forces, reports, training sessions, and other projects involving Meyer. These files include material on Meyer's work with the New York Bureau of Child Welfare (1960-1962).
    - New Jersey DCY Training, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - National Association of Social Workers (NASW) CHAT Child Welfare, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Louise Wise Services, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Bureau of Child Welfare--New York City, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Bureau of Child Welfare--New York City--Reports on Training Program, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Child Welfare--U.S. Children's Bureau, circa 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Temple University Hospital Consultation, 1974 May (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Community Action for Legal Services, Inc. (CALS), 1977 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - New Jersey Department of Youth and Family Services (NY-DYFS), 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Harlem Hospital Consultation, 1967 June-July (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Educational Methods Institute--CUSSW, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Burnout, circa 1980 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Preservation Workshop University of Georgia, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Wilfrid Laurier University, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      (Meyer's report on their doctoral program)
    - Council on Social Work Education (CSWE)--Specialization, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      (Task Force)
- Series III: Publications and Related Files, 1959-1994
  This series contains correspondence, drafts, and reprints related to articles, books, and editorials by Meyer.
  - Assessment in Social Work Practice, circa 1993
    - Chapter VI Graphics (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Chapters, (3 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 4-6)
    - Untitled, 1991, Undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - The Homeless Seriously and Persistently Mentally Ill, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Editorials and Reprints, 1959-1994 (Box 16, Folder 8)